<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>UWG</title><description>Resources and discussion written for unpublished writers by an unpublished writer.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 8 May 2020 10:51:18 -0400</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Fri, 8 May 2020 10:51:18 -0400</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/writing-idea-eating-hunger</guid><title>Writing Is Like Eating: The Hunger and the Work</title><description>An idea, to a writer, is like hunger. It inspires action but it also requires work. You can't eat until you've cooked.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/writing-idea-eating-hunger</link><pubDate>Fri, 8 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You can’t always predict when hunger is going to rumble your insides. You can only hope you’ll have food available when it does, food that’s cooked and ready to eat—not ingredients in the fridge or the pantry. But so many times, that’s what happens: you’re hungry but now you’re facing thirty minutes or an hour of prepping, cooking, baking, etc., and all the while your stomach continues to grumble.</p><p>When an idea leaps into your brain or a thought pops up out of the fresh spring soil of your imagination, you hope you'll be ready for it. Will you have your computer, or notebook, or phone, or, at least, a napkin and a pen, handy and charged and updated or clean and full of ink or lead? Most importantly, you hope you'll have the time and energy at that moment to fire up the engines, to push your brain to 100% function and hold it there, in the red, for thirty minutes or an hour or more.</p><p>You’re eager to realize the idea, to fulfill its promise of greatness. But too often you spend that post-inception adrenaline prepping, writing, deleting and rewriting, struggling to do the work that will create in reality what you envisioned so elegantly in your mind. You’re hungry for the meal but all through the process of cooking it your stomach complains.</p><p>If you aren’t prepared, the idea becomes sadly relegated to a note that’s soon lost in the wilderness of digital clutter or left in a pocket and shredded in the laundry. The thrill of inception—the fuel of creation—is gone and, with it, the motivation to do the work.</p><p>Worse, if you’re unable to store the fleeting idea somewhere, <em>anywhere</em>, it evaporates, forgotten forever. Only the taste of possibility lingers in your mouth. You know it was there, once, new and exciting, but its content and context are gone. You salivate, wishing for the food you desire, hot and fresh, but missing the key ingredients.</p><p>Writing is like eating. Ideas are like hunger. They spark energy, they inspire action, they demand work but they are all too often met with unpreparedness and, much later, with a dull blade, a cool stove, a missing ingredient.</p><h2>Having Written</h2><p>There's a saying I've seen <a href="https://twitter.com/advicetowriters/status/919699417946615808?s=21">attributed to Dorothy Parker</a>:</p><blockquote><p>I hate writing. I love having written.</p></blockquote><p>I love writing when I'm ready for the idea. When I'm not, I empathize with this feeling. I'd much rather <em>have written</em> the thing than stare unmotivated and miserable into the work ahead.</p><p>In the same way, I think, the hungry cook doesn't look forward to cooking. She looks forward to <em>having cooked</em> and, thus, eating.</p><p>But one must eat to survive. Ready or not, you, writer, must write.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/writing-simply-plain-text</guid><title>On Writing Simply: The Beauty of Plain Text Writing</title><description>Plain text is the fastest route from idea to draft. No layout. No styling. No imposing blank page. The writer can get to work.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/writing-simply-plain-text</link><pubDate>Tue, 5 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I wrote this piece on an iPad Pro using a combination of:</p><ol><li><a href="https://helloedit.raphaelkabo.com/">HelloEdit</a></li><li><a href="https://ia.net/">iA Writer</a></li><li>Apple Notes</li><li>and more…</li></ol><p>I discovered HelloEdit via <a href="https://512pixels.net/2019/05/helloedit/">a post on 512pixels.net</a><sup>1</sup>, the very site which, it turns out, <a href="https://512pixels.net/2011/05/markdown-new-word51/">inspired the creation of this tool</a> with an article eight years ago.</p><p>I've never used Word 5.1 or AppleWorks. The earliest memory of writing I have is on the family's blue iMac when I was five or six or seven.</p><p>I must have been using the Microsoft Word of the early 2000s or an equivalent program—I remember its overwhelming (to a six-year-old) toolset, its rows of toolbars and tiny icons—because the thing that sticks with this memory is that I printed the story out on one piece of paper, front and back, in landscape orientation.</p><p>And I printed it in blue font.</p><p>I have no idea why, any of this. I also manually shaped the text on the page (using the Return key—the only way I knew how) to leave the bottom-right quarter of the page blank. In that space, I hand-illustrated the story's first scene with crayons.</p><p>That was my first published work.</p><p>Discovering HelloEdit and reading about the simple origins of text-editing to which it pays homage has led me to realize something, in retrospect. I had never understood plain text writing until I started writing on an iPad.</p><h2>Plain Text</h2><blockquote><p>[Word processors] started trying to help—and helping a writer while he or she is writing is impossible.<sup>2</sup></p></blockquote><p>I suppose TextEdit and Notepad and Apple Notes and the deceased <a href="https://433labs.com/">Plain Text</a> on iOS were my first experiences with pure-text editing. However, the revelation came when I downloaded iA Writer on my iPad. That was when I discovered Markdown.</p><p>I’d read Daring Fireball through its RSS feed but I’d never visited the website long enough to notice <a href="https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">John Gruber's Markdown project</a>. It's the gilding for the kind of plain text writing I'd been doing in short bursts in the Notes app or TextEdit, rendered with simple, clear formatting.</p><p>Markdown is the cure for my incessant urge to format and reformat text more than I write it. It’s incredibly productive. And I enjoy the uniform beauty of watching my progress as I build a sturdy stack of paragraph blocks. Markdown makes the simplicity of plain text beautiful, which makes writing at length in plain text truly pleasant.</p><p>I’ve grown to like using fixed-width fonts (to which I was <a href="https://ia.net/writer/blog/a-typographic-christmas/">turned on by iA Writer, mainly</a>), especially. <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/a-writers-justification/">Full justification is ugly</a>. But rectangular chunks of fixed-width text make me feel accomplished—like I’ve stacked heavy weights at the gym or built a physical object with tools and sweat.</p><p>That old quote about writing being as simple as sitting over a typewriter to bleed? Writing in a word processor feels more like sitting down at a table scattered with various styles of paper, pens, pencils and erasers and having to sort through it all to choose the right combination.</p><p>Plain text writing, on the other hand, feels like an empty room with a pen and a notebook. Or a manual typewriter. Instead of clicking past a template selection window to tinker with line spacing and the right serif or sans-serif font, I can <em>get to work</em>.</p><p>A word processor is called a word <em>processor</em>, after all. It’s better as a tool for <em>processing</em> text: editing, formatting, exporting, publishing.</p><p>Plain text is the writing tool.</p><p>And as a place for writing, it’s less intimidating than a document in a word processor, too. There, you’re faced with a blank page, that imposing monolithic wall in your face. That romanticized foe. Maybe it’s allowed too much power, but it has an effect on me like an unfamiliar darkness. Even with the knowledge that scary movies are just movies and that ghosts aren’t real, the right combination of sleeplessness, cloud cover and unknown noises can put the hairs up on the back of my neck and quicken my breath.</p><p>The fixed blank page is intimidating. It has a length and width and it begins empty, a sign of the work ahead.</p><p>Whereas the plain text editor is an empty creative space without size or shape. A TextEdit window is infinitely resizable and adapts without argument to different window shapes. It’s an endless scroll that doesn’t <em>expect</em> any amount of work. It allows you to write your thoughts with as much concision or flourish as you want, and then export without judgment.</p><p>If I’m exporting plain text to a page-based format, I’m often surprised by the number of pages I’ve written. But regardless of its final form, I feel satisfied knowing that the text I’ve written is just as long as it needs to be.</p><h2>Countless</h2><p>School writing, you'll probably remember, is all about the page count<sup>3</sup>. Your brain in high school:</p><blockquote><p>Keep those paragraphs trim and cut them at the very start of the fourth or fifth line of each one to get the most out of the next paragraph's line break—more white space equals fewer words and fewer words equal less work. Don't break a paragraph too close to the bottom of the page or that pesky word processor will bend the rules and fit it all into the margin.</p></blockquote><p>But <em>writing</em> writing—it's not about page count. It's not about counting at all. Writing is about saying what you need to say in the way that best says it. Regardless of length, shape or line height. Plain text lets you do the essential writing with the bare minimum "help".</p><p>It also gives you the flexibility to continue the work elsewhere, when a more complex or specific environment suits it. Plain text is the tool that you can take with you anywhere.</p><p>iA Writer and other plain text editors—<a href="https://getdrafts.com/">Drafts</a>, for example—provide powerful exporting options. These apps recognize that they are, by definition, merely the starting places for the work. When the writing is finished, the words move on to their destinations: to word processors, to email clients, to HTML files.</p><p>The great achievement of the writer is to have written. No matter the allure of publication or recognition, the writer's ultimate triumph and highest joy comes from the completion of the writing. When it is finished, it is finished. The word processor blinks at an unfortunate, oddly-shaped, two-fifths full final page. The plain text editor does not judge but presents the completed structure of words, ready for what's next.</p><hr><ol><li>HelloEdit revealed itself to me at just the right time: my job had recently “upgraded” me from my personal MacBook Pro to a one-year-newer company MBP that had none of my well-oiled workflows or favorite apps. (But it has that extra click in the trackpad for whatever that’s for!) // Suddenly, instead of writing in iA Writer and exporting, I had Word 2011 (<em>2011!</em>). That’s a good way to kill a writer’s productivity for a few days while they search for alternatives. So I was quite thankful for HelloEdit’s perfect simplicity and that it requires no download or sign up to use it.</li></ol><ol start="2"><li><a href="https://512pixels.net/2011/05/markdown-new-word51/">Markdown is the new Word 5.1 | 512 Pixels</a></li></ol><ol start="3"><li>Page counts are an artifact of the past, like word counts for print magazines or writing a "column". Teachers, please: we understand the need for <em>some</em> kind of metric that requires reluctant students to write more than a few sentences. But do the right thing and teach students to expand their pieces by asking more questions, not by fluffing up the easy answers. (Teaching is difficult, and teachers are due much respect. But for much of my childhood, even the good English teachers failed to teach most of us to write more by engaging more deeply with the subject.)</li></ol>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/giant-venn-diagram</guid><title>The Giant Venn Diagram and Finding Your Niche</title><description>On finding your personalized niche at the center of a giant, world-spanning Venn diagram.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/giant-venn-diagram</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Coming soon…</p><p>An exciting project that will help you find your <strong>personalized writing niche</strong> at the center of a giant, world-spanning Venn diagram.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/find-passion-work-happy</guid><title>How to Find Your Passion and Work Happier</title><description>What would you do, right now, if you had nothing else to do and no bills to pay? That passion is your key to happier, more fulfilling work.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/find-passion-work-happy</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:02:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What would you do right now if you had nothing else to do and no bills to pay?</p><p>Don't say sleep! I mean <em>do</em>: what would you work on, what would you learn, <strong>what would you create</strong>?</p><p>Or, what would you spend forty hours a week doing if that time was all yours, with no financial or social responsibilities attached?</p><p>Would it be what you currently do as your job? My guess is… probably not.</p><h2>What It Means to Do Whatever You Want</h2><p>As you try to answer these questions, remove yourself from the contexts of "career" or "job" or "money".</p><p>This question—<strong>what is your passion</strong>—is a tricky one to answer. It forces you to think far outside of the box of precedence and expectations and far outside of the bounds of your current life.</p><p>Yet, it is, potentially, the greatest contributor to your happiness and fulfillment.</p><h2>Loving Your Job Makes You Exceptional</h2><p>Every day, thousands of people make money by podcasting, playing videogames, writing blog posts, photo-journaling on social media, choreographing dances, operating food trucks, reviewing products… Insert one of your hobbies and someone's probably making a living doing it.</p><p>These aren’t multi-millionaire YouTubers and internet <em>influencers</em>; these are creative, hard-working people who have built audiences and businesses that can support them. They're not mega-stars but they've struck gold. Why? Because they're earning income doing the things they love--many of which simply didn't make money (or even exist) ten or twenty years ago.</p><p>There are thousands of these people. <strong>Thousands of <em>exceptions</em></strong>.</p><p>How have they become exceptions? They've worked extremely hard and dedicated themselves to the things they're passionate about.</p><p>The work is never easy. In fact, that's <em>especially</em> true for these exceptions. But when you're doing something you're passionate about, the <em>hunger</em> to do the work and do it well comes easy. That drives you onward.</p><p>How can you become an exception?</p><p>First, <strong>you need to discover your specific, honest passion</strong>, the thing that you'd prefer to do over anything else. You have to locate that vein of gold before you can start to mine it.</p><h2>How to Find Your Passion</h2><p><a href="https://youtu.be/TMv2i_giboI">Finding your passion</a> is a quest for truth.</p><p>You must dig down through the layers of assumptions, fears and social and societal roadblocks and find the <em>thing</em> that occupies your mind whenever you’re not stressing about everything else.</p><p>What do you daydream about while you’re supposed to be prepping for a meeting or answering emails or replacing spark plugs or serving coffee?</p><p>What’s the thing you crave first after a day at the office or in the field? Videogames? Reading? Writing? Playing an instrument?</p><p>What makes you <em>want</em> to hustle, even after a long day? Do you slurp down leftover pasta while working through chapters of an online course on software development? Do you share photos of every neighborhood you visit and every trip you take? Do you spend most of your evening on dinner, prepping, cooking and plating with such a love for the craft that two hours fly by before you realize you still haven’t <em>eaten</em> any food?</p><p>Start listing everything you like to do and everything you're good at, every skill you've developed and every fascination that's struck you. For each item in the list, decide whether each one of those things is your dream or just a hobby, your passion or merely an interest.</p><p>Try to catch yourself the next time you're doing it, whatever <em>it</em> is—that's it, <strong>you've found your passion</strong>.</p><p><em>(There's a more detailed, more visual way to explore your interests that I'll cover in a separate article soon. That method is equally effective as a tool for writers searching for their personal voice.)</em></p><h2>How to Use Your Passion to Work Happier</h2><p>How can you turn your passion, the thing that drives you, into the thing that sustains you?</p><p>You make it work. You make it into work.</p><p>You discover—or, better yet, <em>invent</em>—a way to monetize it. You practice. Learn. Build a portfolio. Make connections. Gain experience. Volunteer. You start your journey.</p><p>Eventually, you begin charging people for your skill. You work extremely hard to <em>make</em> it successful. You dedicate yourself to building a business around it so that it can grow, sustain itself and, eventually, fund the lifestyle you want.</p><p><strong>Find your career passion. Then make your passion your career.</strong></p><p>Ultimately, it’s your unquenchable love for the thing that will drive you to do better—better than you were the day before and, more importantly, better than the competition. It's what keeps you up at night, dreaming of ideas and improvements. It's what staves off burnout and boredom and that paralyzing fear of failure that stands at the beginning of every new endeavor like a smug-faced villain.</p><p>When you turn your passion into your career you learn to love your work. It's no longer a job. It's the realization of that old cliche: <em>you'll never work a day in your life</em>.</p><h2>Everyone is Almost Famous</h2><p>Some like to say, "Anybody can become famous these days."</p><p>That's oversimplified and inaccurate.</p><p>It's true that we’re living in amazing times, where almost anyone can break into almost any creative field with almost no formal training. Want to learn how to build furniture? Follow a few dozen YouTube tutorials and a few lists of book recommendations. Want to make short films? You can start with a phone and YouTube. Want to write a book? Publish it on Wordpress. Tweet it. <a href="https://www.npr.org/2016/02/27/468402296/-the-martian-started-as-a-self-published-book">Serialize it on your website</a>.</p><p>Getting started is the easy part and it’s becoming easier. As the bar to entry sinks lower, however, competition increases.</p><p>It’s harder to stand out when a hundred million people are publishing videos and blog posts every month, when ten thousand short stories are fighting for a tiny amount of attention on a web platform.</p><p>The internet gives any person with a connection access to information, tools, platforms and a potential audience of billions.</p><p>Sounds easy, doesn't it.</p><p><strong>The world of huge opportunities has always been open to more people than took advantage of it.</strong></p><p>It's hard work being successful. Maybe more people than ever <em>do</em> get their fifteen minutes of fame but how many of them sustain it?</p><p>It takes dedication. More than that, it takes clarity—identifying your passion and focusing all of your energy on making it successful.</p><h2>Don't Chase Your Passion. Activate It.</h2><p>The opportunity is there for you to do the thing you most want to do and, with dedication and patience, turn it into your career. So do it! Stop wasting time daydreaming about it at work or wishing you had another hour of lunch to work on it.</p><p><strong>It's waiting for you to find it, to choose it over everything else and <em>get to work</em>.</strong></p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/stop-hesitating-start-new</guid><title>How to Stop Hesitating and Jump Into Something New</title><description>Do you have a hundred ideas swimming around in your brain-space every day? Learn how to stop dreaming and _start_ that new project you've been dreaming about.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/stop-hesitating-start-new</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:01:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re anything like me, you’ve got a hundred ideas swimming around in your brain-space every day. This can lead to all kinds of difficulty <strong>when it comes to focus</strong> but it can also cause you to miss out on opportunities. When is the <em>right time</em> to finally get started on that project you’ve been dreaming about?</p><p>Maybe you’ve been saving dozens of URLs and videos to your inspiration database or your read-it-later list. Maybe you’ve been fiddling with notes, sketches, mockups, models or brainstorming techniques and, every time you add something new, you think, next week I’ll finally <em>start</em>.</p><p>At some point, you have to conquer your fear, turn on your <strong>focus engine</strong> and begin.</p><p>When is that point? And how can you stop hesitating before you miss your opportunity?</p><h2>Not Enough Time in the Day</h2><p>This was my problem:</p><p>Picture me at my desk, putting the finishing touches on some blog content for a client, sending it away in an email and relishing the blank space of time left in the day to work on <em>my</em> big projects (there are always several, despite my best efforts). I’d look forward to my goals, my creations, my ambitions.</p><p>I’d eat something, take a deep breath, and… feel stuck.</p><p>What to do? What to prioritize? I know I started <em>that</em> yesterday, but I really want to work on <em>this</em> today. I only have—let’s see—three and a half hours before the evening, dinner and family time. I probably couldn’t get <em>this</em> done in that amount of time, so I’ll save it for “tomorrow” (read: “eventually”) and I’ll work on <em>this</em> instead. I guess… Ugh.</p><h2>The Power of Self-Discipline</h2><p>Self-discipline—gross. I know. It’s <em>your</em> ambition—let it run wild!</p><p>We writers tend to be enormous dreamers. Thinking, imagining, living within the fiction we create. But to accomplish your goal and to <a href="https://unpublishedwritersguide.com//articles/how-to-find-passion-work-happier/">make your passion into a successful operation</a>, you have to say no to yourself. You have to set limits, practice <em>a little</em> restraint and do the work.</p><h2>When Am I Ready to Jump Into Something New?</h2><p>The feeling that comes with saying "<a href="https://giphy.com/gifs/3oxOCdmfrrnkNacsJa/html5">I'm ready</a>" to a new project is the same that comes with saying "I'm done" to a finished work. Neither is easy, or clear, or definite. The writer is never finished if left without a deadline.</p><p>Like knowing when you've finished, knowing when to start is about paying attention to your feelings. Notice when you procrastinate and when you think, <em>Maybe I've planned enough.</em> Listen to yourself and realize that there's never going to be the "correct" time to jump in.</p><p>There's risk in every worthwhile endeavor. It might seem scary to start something and be caught under-prepared. But much worse than that is never starting at all.</p><h2>How to Conquer Fear and Finally Begin</h2><p>Starting. Is. Scary.</p><p><em>It might not work</em>, you're thinking. <em>And I'll have wasted hours and days and weeks of time on a thing that failed.</em></p><p>That right there is a recipe for failure. And <em>that</em>, right after it, is a cliche but it's also true. Nothing is guaranteed to work and hard work doesn't guarantee success. But letting the fear of failure overwhelm you all but guarantees a hard time.</p><p>This isn't a pep talk about believing in yourself and diving blindly into the next idea you have. It's about having confidence in the idea that you obviously think has merit, or you wouldn't have spent the last six weeks or months or years wavering about starting it.</p><p>You have more ideas in a day than you probably realize because most of them are so bad they simply float right away and disintegrate. But a few stick around. They're the ones to pay attention to. And if you've got a few coming back day after day, then it's time to dig in and decided which one is the <em>really</em> good one, which one leads to the vein of gold.</p><p><a href="https://unpublishedwritersguide.com//articles/how-to-find-passion-work-happier/">Which one are you passionate about?</a></p><p>I kept coming back to the idea for this website, day after day, as I wrote fiction and clients' blog posts and marketing copy￼. I just kept thinking about the vast world of writing and what my niche could be.</p><p>And I thought there was a message that I wasn't hearing enough: "publication" could be subjective, could be the achievement of one's goal, whatever that was. You can define what publication means for your writing.</p><p>For me, it was simply to earn a living with my writing, but that means <em>my</em> writing--not a client's assignments or an editor's pitches. Whether it's fiction or this website or guest writing somewhere else, I wanted to turn my passion for writing into a sustainable business.</p><p>I thought about what it meant to write as an unpublished writer for weeks before I considered its potential as a website collecting essays on this topic. I brainstormed and planned what that website might look like for months. The idea evolved in the back of my mind for months while I commuted to work, during lunch and in the evenings. It survived the transition to freelancing and an out-of-state move. It survived digressions to other projects I'd begun.</p><p>It proved its merit by sticking in my mind for nearly a year. And now, it's real.</p><p>There might not be specific day on which you decide, <em>today's the day</em>. It might simply be <strong>the transition from passively thinking to actively creating</strong>. Whichever it is, recognize that you've taken that step and commit yourself to the idea.</p><p>That's the time to stop hesitating and <em>start</em>.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/why-write-for-no-one</guid><title>Why Write for No One? Celebrating the Drive to Write</title><description>Writing is hard but many of us do it for no one, for free, for fun. Why? There's one simple and important reason. Let's explore the passion that drives writers.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/why-write-for-no-one</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Writing is hard. Yet, many of us do it for no one, for free, for <em>fun</em>. Why?</p><p>The answers are various:</p><ul><li>It's fun to imagine stories.</li><li>It's fascinating to explore other minds.</li><li>It's thrilling.</li><li>It's therapeutic.</li><li>It's cathartic.</li><li>It's my dream.</li><li>I love the art of arranging words.</li><li>I love reading and reading makes me want to write stories.</li><li>I cannot stop myself from telling stories.</li></ul><p>Artists of other media and trades surely use the same reasons among their friends and peers. It's natural for us. For non-artists, though, these answers are unsatisfactory. <em>You're not being published. You're not being paid. Is anyone even reading what you write?</em></p><p>For the person whose work is not their passion, money is the reason they do what they do. Some of those people might have hobbies. An investment banker who knits or a receptionist who fishes or a police officer who builds LEGO models exerts a significant amount of effort and practices great patience without any expected return. Zero dollars, zero acclaim. It's what they enjoy and that's enough payoff.</p><p>Similarly, there's nothing wrong with writing while having no interest in being read. Writing can be a hobby.</p><p>The difference between the unpublished writer and the hobbyist is deceptively simple: it is our desire to, at some point, <em>be published</em>. We are the writers who write for no one but who also write with care and passion and with the hope of one day being read, of being loved, of being paid.</p><p>Writing that's for no one but ourselves is not wasted. It's practice, it's habit-forming, it's unstoppable: it's the thing we're thinking about even when we're doing other, paying work.</p><p>Whether it's literary fiction, fan fiction, a personal blog, song lyrics or something else, every piece of the unpublished writer's work is another step toward publication.</p><h2>What is Publication?</h2><p>Publication doesn't necessarily mean a book deal. For the unpublished writer, it can simply mean graduating to a thousand readers from a hundred, or to a hundred from ten. It can mean selling a piece to a prominent journal or website. It can mean going viral. It can simply mean corresponding with five enthusiastic fans via email or Twitter.</p><p>Publication is defined by each of us. And each of us knows that publication is not the end of the journey; it just resets the meter. The published author's next goal looks familiar: publication, again.</p><p>Why write for no one? The question is unimportant. If you love writing, write. Write it in a notebook, type it on a computer, post it to a blog or your social media, mail it to your sibling or your friend, tape it to the inside of your car's rear window and let people read it while you're parked at a restaurant--just put it out there. That pressure is enough to <em>make</em> you edit carefully, trust me.</p><p>It's not easy to write for no one, even if you love writing. It's hard work and it's easy to get discouraged.</p><p>The thing is, getting paid to write doesn't make it easier.</p><p>I spent a year at a digital marketing agency writing for clients' blogs. The money didn't make the writing easier. I still cared about producing the highest-quality writing. I still toiled over the small edits and stressed about word choices. The money only made justifying my writing to others easier.</p><p>Stop trying to justify your passion to people who insist on asking you <em>why</em>. There's no help to be had from them, anyway. It's your passion and it's your responsibility.</p><p>So take responsibility and do it. Like everyone who's ever written a piece on getting published says, <strong>you can't get published if you don't write</strong>.</p><p>Write because you love to write. Write for no one, because you're not actually writing for no one. You're writing for yourself.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>