<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content"><channel><title>Unpublished Writer's Guide to Writing for No One</title><description>Resources and discussion written for unpublished writers by an unpublished writer.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/</link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 17:22:48 -0400</lastBuildDate><pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 17:22:48 -0400</pubDate><ttl>250</ttl><atom:link href="https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/feed.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/how-to-stop-hesitating-start-something-new</guid><title>How to Stop Hesitating and Jump Into Something New</title><description>Do you have a hundred ideas swimming around in your brain-space every day? Learn how to stop dreaming and _start_ that new project you've been dreaming about.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/how-to-stop-hesitating-start-something-new</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Mar 2020 17:22:13 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you’re anything like me, you’ve got a hundred ideas swimming around in your brain-space every day. This can lead to all kinds of difficulty when it comes to focus[^link → future article] but it can also [cause you to miss out on opportunities]. When is the <em>right time</em> to finally get started on that project you’ve been dreaming about?</p><p>Maybe you’ve been saving dozens of URLs and videos to your inspiration[^link → future] database or your read-it-later list. Maybe you’ve been fiddling with notes, sketches, mockups, models or brainstorming techniques[^link → future] and, every time you add something new, you think, next week I’ll finally <em>start</em>.</p><p>At some point, you have to conquer your fear, turn on your <strong>focus engine</strong> and begin.</p><p>When is that point? And how can you stop hesitating before you miss your opportunity?</p><h2>Personal story</h2><p>This was (one of) my problem(s):</p><p>Picture me at my desk, putting the finishing touches on some blog content for a client, sending it away in an email and relishing the blank space of time left in the day to work on <em>my</em> big projects (because there are always several, despite my best efforts). I’d look forward to my goals, my creations, my ambitions.</p><p>I’d eat something, take a deep breath, and… feel stuck.</p><p>What to do? What to prioritize? I know I started <em>that</em> yesterday, but I really want to work on <em>this</em> today. I only have—let’s see—three and a half hours before the evening, dinner and [family] time. I probably couldn’t even get <em>this</em> done in that amount of time, so I’ll save it for “tomorrow” (read: “sometime in the future”) and I’ll work on <em>this</em> instead. I guess… Ugh.</p><h2>Self-Discipline</h2><p>Gross. I know. It’s <em>your</em> ambition—let it run wild!</p><p>We writers tend to be enormous dreamers. Thinking, imagining, living within the fiction we create. But to accomplish your goal and to make your passion into a successful operation[^link: /articles/how-to-find-passion-work-happier], you have to say no to yourself. You have to set limits, [show restraint] and do the work.</p><h2>When am I ready to jump into something new?</h2><p>The feeling that comes with saying "<a href="link-SpongeBob">I'm ready</a>" to a new project is the same that comes with saying "I'm done" to a finished work. Neither is easy, or clear, or definite. The writer is never finished if left without a deadline.</p><p>Like knowing when you've finished, knowing when to start is about paying attention to your feelings. Notice when you procrastinate and equally when you think, <em>Maybe I've planned enough.</em> Listen to yourself and realize that there's never going to be the "correct" time to jump in. It might seem scary to start something possibly with too little planning. But much worse is never starting at all because the fear of being caught unprepared won't let you.</p><p>There's risk in every worthwhile endeavor.</p><h2>How to Conquer fear and jump into something new</h2><p>Starting. Is. Scary.</p><p><em>It might not work</em>, you're thinking. <em>And I'll have wasted hours and days and weeks of time on a thing that failed.</em></p><p>That right there is a recipe for failure. And <em>that</em>, right after it, is a cliche but it's also true. Nothing is guaranteed to work. And hard work doesn't guarantee success. But letting yourself be overwhelmed by the fear of failure all but guarantees a hard time.</p><p>This isn't a pep talk about believing in yourself and being courageous in the face of a plainly bad idea. It's about having confidence in the idea that you obviously think has merit, or you wouldn't have spent the last six weeks or months or years wavering about starting it.</p><p>You have more ideas in a day than you probably realize because most of them are so bad they simply float right away and disintegrate. But a few stick and they're the ones to pay attention to. And if you've got a few coming back day after day, then it's time to dig in and decided which one is the <em>really</em> good one, which one leads to the vein of gold.</p><p><a href="https://unpublishedwritersguide.com//articles/how-to-find-your-passion/">Which one are you passionate about?</a></p><p>I kept coming back to the idea for this website, day after day, as I wrote fiction and dreamed about publication and wrote marketing copy and client blog posts and just kept thinking about all the kinds of writing and all the possibilities for "publication" that exist and that I wasn't considering.</p><p>And I thought it was a message that I wasn't hearing enough: publication could be subjective, could be the achievement of one's goal, whatever that was. You can define what publication means for your writing. And I think clearly defining that helps shorten the journey from here to there. To the unpublished writer, publication seems like it's miles of winding unpaved paths away. But that's the capitalized, idealistic "Publication." The real publication is your own definition and that specificity makes it much closer because the steps to get there are so much clearer.</p><p>For me, it was simply to earn a living with my writing, but that means <em>my</em> writing--not a client's assignments or an editor's pitches. Whether it's fiction or this website or guest writing somewhere else, I wanted to turn my passion for writing into a sustainable business.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/why-write-for-no-one</guid><title>Why Write for No One?</title><description>Writing is hard. Yet, many of us do it for no one, for free, for fun. Why?</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/why-write-for-no-one</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Mar 2020 14:19:59 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Writing is hard. Yet, many of us do it for no one, for free, for <em>fun</em>. Why?</p><p>The answers are various:</p><ul><li>It's fun to imagine stories.</li><li>It's fascinating to explore other minds.</li><li>It's thrilling.</li><li>It's therapeutic.</li><li>It's cathartic.</li><li>It's my dream.</li><li>I love the art of arranging words.</li><li>I love reading and reading makes me want to write stories.</li><li>I cannot stop myself from telling stories.</li></ul><p>Artists of other media and trades must use the same reasons among their friends and peers. It's natural for us. For non-artists, though, these answers are unsatisfactory. <em>You're not being published. You're not being paid. Is anyone reading what you write?</em></p><p>For the person whose work is not their passion, money is the reason they do what they do. Some of those people might have hobbies. An investment banker who knits or a receptionist who fishes or a police officer who builds LEGO models exerts a significant amount of effort and practices great patience without any expected return. Zero dollars, zero acclaim. It's what they enjoy and that's enough payoff.</p><p>Similarly, there's nothing wrong with writing while having no interest in being read. Writing can be a hobby.</p><p>The difference between the unpublished writer and the hobbyist is deceptively simple: it is our desire to, at some point, <em>be published</em>. We are the writers who write for no one but who also write with care and passion and with the hope of one day being read, of being loved, of being paid.</p><p>Writing that's for no one but ourselves is not wasted. It's practice, it's habit-forming, it's unstoppable: it's the thing we're thinking about even when we're doing other, paying work.</p><p>Whether it's literary fiction, fan fiction, a personal blog, song lyrics or something else, every piece of the unpublished writer's work is another step toward publication.</p><h2>What is Publication?</h2><p>Publication doesn't necessarily mean a book deal. For the unpublished writer, it can simply mean graduating to a thousand readers from a hundred, or a hundred from ten. It can mean selling a piece to a prominent journal or website. It can mean going viral. It can simply mean corresponding with five enthusiastic readers via email or Twitter.</p><p>Publication is defined by each of us. And each of us knows that publication is not the end of the journey; it just resets the meter. The published author's next goal looks familiar: publication, again.</p><p>Why write for no one? The question is unimportant. If you love writing, write. Write it in a notebook, type it on a computer, post it to a blog or your social media, mail it to your sibling or your friend, tape it to the inside of your car's rear window and let people read it while you're parked at a restaurant--just put it out there. That pressure is enough to <em>make</em> you edit carefully, trust me.</p><p>It's not easy to write for no one, even if you love writing. It's hard work and it's easy to get discouraged.</p><p>The thing is, getting paid to write doesn't make it easier.</p><p>I spent a year at a digital marketing agency writing for clients' blogs. The money didn't make the writing easier. I still cared about producing the highest-quality writing. I still toiled over small edits and stressed about word choices. The money only made justifying my writing to others easier.</p><p>Stop trying to justify your passion to people who insist on asking you <em>why</em>. There's no help to be had from them, anyway. It's your passion and it's your responsibility.</p><p>So take responsibility and do it. Like everyone who's ever written a piece on getting published says, <strong>You can't get published if you don't write</strong>.</p><p>Write because you love to write. Write for no one, because you're not actually writing for no one. You're writing for yourself.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/giant-venn-diagram</guid><title>The Giant Venn Diagram and Finding Your Niche</title><description>On finding your personalized niche at the center of a giant, world-spanning Venn diagram.</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/giant-venn-diagram</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 19:04:21 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On finding your personalized niche at the center of a giant, world-spanning Venn diagram.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/how-to-find-passion-work-happier</guid><title>How to Find Your Passion, Work Happier and Do What You Want</title><description>What would you do, right now, if you had nothing else to do and no bills to pay? What is your passion?</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/how-to-find-passion-work-happier</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 12:03:11 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What would you do right now if you had nothing else to do and no bills to pay?</p><p>Don't say sleep. I mean <em>do</em>: what would you work on, what would you learn, what would you create?</p><p>What would you spend forty hours a week doing if that time was [completely] for yourself, not for money or responsibility or social necessity?</p><p>Would it be the thing you currently do as your job? My guess is… probably not.</p><h2>What It Means to Do Whatever You Want</h2><p>Remove yourself from the context of "career" or "employment” or "job".</p><p>I want you to consider everything you like to do and decide whether each one of those things is your dream or just a hobby, your passion or merely an interest.</p><p>This question, <em>what's your passion</em>, is a tricky one to answer. It forces you to think far outside of the box of precedence and expectations and far outside of your current life.</p><h2>Loving Your Job Makes You Exceptional</h2><p>Every day, thousands of people make money by podcasting, playing videogames, writing blog posts, photo-journaling on social media, inventing dances, opening food trucks, reviewing products… insert one of your hobbies and someone's probably making a living [on it].</p><p>These aren’t multi-millionaire YouTubers and internet <em>influencers</em>; these are creative, hard-working people who have built audiences large enough to support them. They're not mega-stars but they've struck gold. They're earning income doing the things they love--many of which simply didn't make money (or, in some cases, didn't even exist) ten or twenty years ago.</p><p>There are thousands of these people. <strong>Yet, they are <em>exceptions</em></strong>.</p><p>How do these people become exceptions? They work extremely hard and dedicate themselves to the thing they want to do.</p><p>It's important to remember that the work is never easy; but the <em>hunger</em> to do the work comes easy to someone who's doing what they [truly] want.</p><p>How can you become an exception?</p><p>First, <strong>you need to discover your very specific passion</strong>, the thing that you'd prefer to do over anything else. You have to locate the [vein] of gold before you can start to mine it.</p><h2>Everyone is Almost Famous</h2><p>Cynics like to say, "Anybody can become famous these days."</p><p>That's oversimplified and inaccurate.</p><p>It's true that we’re living in amazing times, where almost anyone can break into almost any field with almost no formal training. Want to learn how to build furniture? Follow a few dozen YouTube tutorials and a few lists of book recommendations. Want to make short films? You can start with a phone and YouTube. Want to write a book? Publish it on Wordpress. Tweet it. Build a website for it[^Link to The Martian? or a story about its self-publication], for free, in a few minutes.</p><p>Getting started is the easy part and it’s becoming easier. As the [bar of entry drops lower, however, competition increases.</p><p>It’s harder to stand out when a hundred million people are publishing videos and blog posts every month, when ten thousand short stories are fighting for a tiny amount of attention on a web platform.</p><p>The internet gives any person with a connection access to information, tools, platforms and a <em>potential</em> audience of billions.</p><p>However, it in no way makes it easy to become "famous".</p><p><strong>The world of huge opportunities has always been open to more people than took advantage of it.</strong></p><p>It's hard work being successful. Maybe more people than ever <em>do</em> get their fifteen minutes of fame but how many of them sustain it?</p><p>It takes dedication. More than that, it takes clarity--identifying your passion and using the natural drive that comes with a passion for something to make it successful.</p><p>So what do you want to do? What would you do for 8+ hours a day if you… could?</p><p>That’s your passion.</p><h2>How to Find Your Passion</h2><p>How do you find your passion[^Find Your Grail on YouTube]?</p><p>It's a quest for truth. Dig down through the layers of assumptions, fears and social and societal roadblocks and find the <em>thing</em> that occupies your mind whenever you’re not stressing about everything else. What do you daydream about while you’re [supposed to be] prepping for a meeting or answering emails or replacing spark plugs or serving coffee?</p><p>What’s the thing you crave first after a day at the office or in the field? Videogames? Reading? Writing? Playing guitar?</p><p>What makes you <em>want</em> to hustle, even after a long day? Do you slurp down leftover pasta while working through chapters of an online course in iOS development? Do you share photos of every neighborhood you visit and every trip you take? Do you spend most of your evening on dinner, prepping, cooking and plating with such a love for the craft that two hours flies by before you realize you still haven’t <em>eaten</em> any food?</p><p>Try to catch yourself the next time you're doing it, whatever it is, and realize: <strong>you've found your passion</strong>.</p><h2>What to Do With Your Passion</h2><p>How can you turn your passion, the thing that drives you, into the thing that sustains you?</p><p>You make it work. You make it into work.</p><p>You discover—or, better yet, <em>invent</em>—a way to monetize it. You practice. Learn. Build a portfolio. Make connections. Gain experience. Volunteer. Barter.</p><p>Then, you start charging people for your skill. You work extremely hard to <em>make</em> it successful. You dedicate yourself to building a business around it so that it can grow, [sustain] itself and, eventually, fund the lifestyle you want.</p><p><strong>Find your career passion. Then make your passion your career.</strong></p><p>Make a plan to make money from the thing you love because the drive to do it is already there and the drive to do it <em>better</em> almost certainly is, too. That drive to do better is the most important thing for a self-starting entrepreneur because it’s what will keep you up at night, thinking of ways to improve your performance so that you’re better than you were the day before and, eventually, better than the competition.</p><p>Ultimately, it’s your unquenchable love for the thing that will drive you to be better than anyone else, that will help you avoid burnout, and boredom, and that paralyzing fear of failure that sits at the beginning of every new endeavor like a [bridge troll].</p><p>When you turn your passion into your career you [learn to] love your job. It's your dream job. It's no longer a job. It's the fulfillment of the cliche: <em>you'll never work a day in your life</em>.</p><p>[The point is,] the opportunity is there for you to do the thing you most want to do and make money from it. So do it! Stop wasting time daydreaming about it at work or wishing you had another hour to do it. It's more than possible; it's realistic.</p><p>The opportunity is there to love your job, to have the happiest work life by doing the thing that makes you happy. Use your passion to make that passion successful.</p>]]></content:encoded></item><item><guid isPermaLink="true">https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/test-process</guid><title>Test Article</title><description>Test post with tag process</description><link>https://unpublishedwritersguide.com/articles/test-process</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 12:00:29 -0400</pubDate><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process</p><p>Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process</p><p>Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process Test post with tag process.</p>]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>